Finding aid to the Alfred Vance Churchill Papers CA.MS.00079
Smith College Archives
Alfred Vance Churchill Papers
1828-1965
Smith College Archives
Churchill, Alfred Vance, 1864-1949.
CA.MS.00079
1.667 linear feet (4 containers)
Professor of Fine Arts. Collection contains biographical material, correspondence, material related to museum and art collecting, publications, and teaching materials.
Biographical / Historical
Alfred Vance Churchill was born on August 14, 1864 in Oberlin, Ohio. He was the son of Charles Henry Churchill, a professor at Oberlin College and his second wife, Henrietta Vance Churchill. Alfred was the second child of Henrietta Vance Churchill, and was the sixth of Charles Henry Churchill's nine children. After studies at Oberlin, Alfred studied art in Berlin, Leipzig, and Paris from 1887-1890. He married Marie Marschall in 1890. Their son Louis Nelson Churchill was born in 1897. In 1892 Churchill directed the art department at Iowa College, Grinnell, Iowa. From 1893-1897, he taught art in the High and Normal Schools of St. Louis, Missouri. In 1897, he was made professor of art and Director of the Department of Fine Arts at Teachers College, Columbia University. He received the degree of Master of Arts from Oberlin College in 1898. Columbia University dismissed Churchill in 1904, but gave him a grant to study and paint in Paris 1904-1906. Smith College hired him in 1905 as the first resident professor in the appreciation and history of art. During his years at Smith, he expanded the Smith College Art Museum into one of the outstanding collections in the United States. A noted art critic, lecturer as well as a teacher and painter (whose work appeared in the Armory Show in Chicago in 1913), he influenced the standards of art teaching, especially as vice-president of the College Art Association. After 27 years of service to Smith, Churchill retired in 1932, staying in Northampton, Massachusetts, and devoting himself to painting and writing. He died on December 29, 1949.
Scope and Contents
There is copious correspondence with important art collectors and figures in the history of Smith College, as well as other educational institutions such as Columbia University. Researchers interested in Oberlin College, family history and the social history of the Midwestern U.S. will find the manuscripts and typescripts of his unpublished book Midwestern of interest. Genealogists will find some mention and dating of family names coming out of New England such as Franklin and Churchill. Art historians will be interested to note Churchill's writings and lectures on the teaching of art, and his role in developing an American taste for French Romantic painters.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into four series:
I. Biographical Materials
II. General and Professional Correspondence
III. Museum and Art Collecting
IV. Publications and Teaching Materials
Arrangement
There is some overlap in categories, but in keeping with the "respect des fonds," it was thought best to retain where possible the arrangement of certain folders which Churchill himself devised.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Alfred Vance Churchill donated letters, photographs, poems, etc. from his own papers in 1941. Later in the same year he donated more files for his biographical record. Two letters written to the Smith College Archivist in 1941 or 1942 substantiate this as the year of donation, although nothing precludes the possibility of donations at an earlier date. On April 26, 1966, Mrs. Bernard A. Churchill [daughter-in-law] donated on behalf of Mrs. A. V. Churchill, a "MS of Oberlin book-typescript and carbon," written by Alfred Vance Churchill, which corresponds to the folders titled "Midwestern."
Art--Study and teaching--Massachusetts--Northampton.; Middle West--History.; Churchill, Alfred Vance, 1864-1949.; Churchill, Charles H. (Charles Henry), 1824-1904.; Churchill family.; Smith College--Faculty.; Smith College. Museum of Art.; Columbia University. Teachers College--Faculty.; Oberlin College--History--Sources.; Binyon, Laurence, 1869-1943.; Burton, Marion Le Roy, 1874-1925.; Dewey, John, 1859-1952.; Freer, Charles Lang, 1856-1919.; Seelye, Laurenus Clark, 1837-1924.; Tryon, Dwight William, 1849-1925.; Walpole, Hugh, Sir, 1884-1941.; White, Henry Cooke, 1861-
- Series I. Biographical Material, 1828-1942
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes correspondence, news clippings, chronologies, obituary, and materials regarding retirement from Smith College and departure from Columbia University. This series also contains family history documents, including photographs, correspondence, and assorted other materials.
  - Letters to Smith College Archives., 1941-42 (Box 708)
  - Biographical materials and chronology. Includes obituary. (Box 708)
    - Retirement from Smith College. (Includes letters from Stephan Bourgeois, Gordon B. Washburn, J. B. Neumann, Frank Jewett Mather, Daniel Catton Rich, Walter Pach, W. R. Valentiner, Edward Alden Jewell), 1931-35 (Box 708)
    - Columbia Teachers College. (Includes letters from John Dewey and James E. Russell), 1897-1939 (Box 708)
  - Photographs: Alfred Vance Churchill and family. (Includes Charles Henry Churchill and sister Lucretia Churchill in 1842, Henrietta Vance Churchill, Polly Franklin Churchill, Emilie von Zulich 1828, David Carroll Churchill), 1828-1932; undated (Box 708)
  - Genealogy materials. (Includes letters from Mrs. William A. Whitney and Benjamin E. Franklin), 1936; undated (Box 708)
    - Genealogy book: The Churchills of Oberlin, 1965 (Box 708)
    - Genealogical materials: Henrietta Beach Vance [grandmother]. (Includes materials about and letters of Henrietta Beach Vance to Alfred and Marie Churchill, materials related to the Vance family in Lagrange County, and to Lewis Nelson Churchill), 1894-1936 (Box 708)
  - Will and account book of Henrietta Beach Vance [grandmother]., 1886-1901 (Box 708)
  - Obituaries of Henrietta Vance Churchill [mother]., 1898-99 (Box 708)
  - Letters and writings of Henrietta Vance Churchill [mother]., 1858; 1892-93 (Box 708)
  - Letters of Charles Henry Churchill [father] to Alfred and Marie Churchill, 1890-1904 (Box 708)
  - Letters to Charles Henry Churchill from family. (Includes photograph and postcard from Lyme, New Hampshire), 1838-43; undated (Box 708)
  - Materials on Charles Henry Churchill [father]., 1872-1936 (Box 708)
  - Letters from brothers and sisters., 1898-1941; undated (Box 708)
  - Letters to family from Berlin., 1888-90 (Box 708)
  - Family letter., 1895 (Box 708)
  - Family letter about Edward [brother]., 1933-34 (Box 708)
- Series II. General and Professional Correspondence, 1889-1942
  This series contains correspondence relating to Churchill's research and and career at Smith College.
  - General correspondence., 1901-42 (Box 708)
  - Letters from Laurence Binyon, 1914-34 (Box 708)
  - Correspondence with Marion LeRoy Burton, 1914-17 (Box 708)
  - Letters from Charles Lang Freer, 1913-16 (Box 708)
  - Letters to Grace Gilfillan, 1901-04 (Box 708)
  - Correspondence with Laurenus Clark Seelye, 1905-15 (Box 708)
  - Correspondence with Dwight William Tryon, 1912-25 (Box 708)
  - Letters from Alice B. Tryon, 1926; undated (Box 708)
  - Letters from Hugh Walpole, 1922-26 (Box 708)
  - Letters from Henry C. White, 1929 (Box 708)
- Series III. Museum and Art Collecting Materials, 1905-1941
  This series includes materials related to museum exhibitions and art collecting, and Churchill's own art work.
  - Gericault exhibit: brochure and correspondence, 1929-36 (Box 709)
  - Booklet on art collecting: "Building a Collection" Full title: Building a Collection: Notes on the Work of Alfred Vance Churchill. Published by the American Association of University Women, 1937? (Box 709)
  - Catalogues of the Smith College Museum of Art. One of the two copies is annotated by Churchill., 1937 (Box 709)
  - Materials on Churchill's art and exhibits. Includes news clippings, brochure and correspondence., 1905-50; undated (Box 709)
  - Silhouettes of Smith College presidents. Includes correspondence., 1938-39 (Box 709)
- Series IV. Publications and Teaching Materials, 1900-1948
  This series includes professional publications, course syllabi, lecture notes, speeches on art education, and transcripts of Churchill's book Midwestern.
  - Prints used for courses Art 13 & 14, undated (Box 709)
  - Lecture notes and outlines for art history. Materials are printed, handwritten, or typed., 1917-18; undated (Box 709)
  - Materials on teaching art. Includes syllabi, correspondence., 1900-41 (Box 709)
  - Speeches and materials on art in education, 1902-30; undated (Box 709)
  - Article: "The Meaning and Aim of Art in Education", 1904 (Box 709)
  - Article: "Art in the College Course", 1915 (Box 709)
  - Booklet: "One Hour Course in Art Interpretation", 1907 (Box 709)
  - List of publications, 1932 (Box 710)
  - Pamphlet: "Catalogue of Architects, Sculptors & Painters", 1907 (Box 709)
  - Pamphlet: "Italian Painters of the Renaissance", 1914 (Box 709)
  - Article: "Picasso's Failure", 1925 (Box 709)
  - Article: "On Cezanne", 1932 (Box 709)
  - Typescript: translations of German songs, 1941-48 (Box 709)
  - Book: Golden Songs. Two copies, one annotated., 1947 (Box 709)
  - Carbon typescript bound: "The Thirteenth Century", undated (Box 709)
  - Manuscript: poems, 1904; undated (Box 709)
  - Midwestern
    - Background materials for Midwestern, 1902-40 (Box 709)
    - Correspondence regarding families of Oberlin, Ohio. (Box 709)
    - Background materials for Midwestern, 1935-38 (Box 709)
    - Background materials for Midwestern. This folder was also arranged by Churchill himself., 1935-38 (Box 710)
    - Manuscript of Midwestern, first folder, undated (Box 710)
    - Manuscript of Midwestern, second folder, undated (Box 710)
    - Manuscript of Midwestern, third folder, undated (Box 710)
    - Manuscript of Midwestern, fourth folder, undated (Box 710)
    - Midwestern MS typed: Preface, Prelude, Chapters 1-7. Appears to be the latest and abridged version of the work. Includes table of contents and a photo of Mrs. Churchill., March 1941 (Box 711)
    - Midwestern MS typed: Chapters 8-13, March 1941 (Box 711)
    - Midwestern MS typed: Chapters 14-17, March 1941 (Box 711)
    - Midwestern MS typed: Chapters 18-23, March 1941 (Box 711)
    - Typescript of Midwestern: Chapters 1-9, February 1941 (Box 711)
      General
      [See Churchill's note in front about the different versions.]
    - Typescript of Midwestern: Chapters 10-13, February 1941 (Box 711)
    - Typescript of Midwestern: Chapters 14-21, February 1941 (Box 711)
    - Typescript of Midwestern: Chapters 22-26, February 1941 (Box 711)